# STEFANO CASTRO TOGNINI

Oak Ridge National Laboratory

@ togninis@ornl.gov

Stognini

in stognini



Research Scientist at Oak Ridge National Laboratory working on computational High Energy Physics (HEP). His main effort is focused on Celeritas, a GPU Monte Carlo (MC) detector simulation code for HEP that will enable the use of DOE's Leadership Computing Facilities—such as Frontier and Summit—by HEP experiments. In the past he was a collaborator on MINOS and NOvA, managed by Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory (Fermilab). These are long-term multi-million dollar endeavors built to understand the nature of neutrinos and answer fundamental questions related to astrophysics, dark matter, and more. His 7+ years of experience, working with diversified teams led to many published data analyses using C++, Python, ROOT, shell scripting, parallel computing, and MC simulations. Software development is managed using GIT, allied with automated code referencing (Doxygen). Production of technical documentation is routinely done. He also has experience teaching at undergraduate level, mentoring graduate students, presenting technical seminars, and talking to the public at science outreach events.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Research Scientist

Scalable Engineering Applications

Computational Sciences and Engineering Division

### Oak Ridge National Laboratory

## 2023 - Present

Oak Ridge (TN), U.S.

#### Postdoctoral Research Associate

**HPC Methods for Nuclear Applications** 

Nuclear Energy and Fuel Cycle Division

# Oak Ridge National Laboratory

**#** 2019 − 2023

Oak Ridge (TN), U.S.

#### COLLABORATIONS

## Celeritas Project

github.com/celeritas-project

## 2020 - Present

ORNL

A GPU Monte Carlo particle transport code for HEP experiments.

DOE **CODE**: 10.11578/dc.20221011.1

# **URL Muon Detector Project**

## 2020 - Present

**♀** ORNL

A compact muon detector developed to test and validate new non-destructive techniques for Geological Disposal Safety Assessments (GDSA).

## **NO** $\nu$ **A** Experiment

% novaexperiment.fnal.gov

**#** 2013 − 2018

**♀** Fermilab / ANL / UFG

Leading author of Phys. Rev. D 99, 122004.

• Contributed to Phys. Rev. D 104, 012014.

# MINOS/MINOS+ Experiment

% www-numi.fnal.gov

## 2011 - Present

**♀** Fermilab / ANL / UFG

Contributed to Phys. Rev. D 91, 112006 / Phys. Rev. D 93, 052017.

### **PUBLICATIONS**

# **SOFT SKILLS**

**Teaching** Mentoring Science outreach Portuguese (native) **English** Italian

## **HARD SKILLS**

French

Technical skills Data analysis Monte Carlo simulation Data structuring Parallel computing

Programming & scripting languages

C/C++ | Python | SQL | Shell **ETFX** 

Frameworks, libraries & tools

art | GIT Doxygen Geant4 **ROOT CORSIKA** Spack LSF **TORQUE** 

#### **EDUCATION**

Ph.D. in Physics - High Energy Physics

# **Federal University of Goias**

Funding: CAPES, CNPq, ANL

**#** 2012 − 2018 ♀ Goiania (GO), Brazil **DOE** OSTI www.osti.gov/biblio/1468447

M.Sc. in Physics - High Energy Physics

## **Federal University of Goias**

Funding: CAPES, Fermilab

**#** 2010 − 2012 **♀** Goiania (GO), Brazil

B.Sc. in Physics

## **Federal University of Goias**

**≅** 2005 − 2009

♀ Goiania (GO), Brazil

**i** iNSPIRE HEP | inspirehep.net/authors/1074966